Finding Aid for Delta Sigma Delta records, 1882-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Delta Sigma Delta records 1882-1982
Delta Sigma Delta.
2 oversize items
22 linear feet 20 boxes and bound records and artifacts on display in DSD Room
851133 Bd 2
National dental fraternity founded at University of Michigan. Constitution and by-laws, minutes, financial records, fraternity newsletter, memorabilia and artifacts, textbooks, citations and plaques, photographs, and miscellaneous manuscripts.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of Delta Sigma Delta (Donor no. 4812 ) have come to the library in various accessions.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
Delta Sigma Delta, the first dental fraternity, was founded on November 15, 1882 at the University of Michigan by Charles Howard and a group of six other dental students. The seven founding members of the fraternity were Charles W. Howard, Louis J. Mitchell, Clarence J. Hand, Ezra L. Kern, Louis Manning James, Lyndall L. Davis, and Francis E. Cassidy, who were followed into membership soon after by three additional students, Charles P. Weinrich, Donald D. Magill, and William Cleland. Delta Sigma Delta, the name selected by transposing the last two letters of the dental degree, D.D.S., began recording minutes in January of 1883.
On February 23, 1884, a Supreme Chapter consisting of the graduating seniors was created. Within the hierarchy of the organization, the fraternity is governed by the Supreme Chapter. Undergraduate chapter members, of which there are many throughout the country, are still in dental school, but upon graduation, they may be accepted on merit into the Supreme Chapter. Graduate chapters, or auxiliaries, are divisions of the Supreme Chapter, organized regionally. Delta Sigma Delta also operates many Graduate Chapters throughout the world, including New Zealand and Australia. From its founding, Delta Sigma Delta was intended to be a social fraternity open to both dental students and to dentists in practice.
The idea for a historical library/museum began in 1926, primarily through the efforts of Dr. Frank O. Clifford. When it was determined that it was not practical to house the museum at the Alpha Chapter House in Ann Arbor, fraternity members began looking for another site. Not until 1972 did the historical materials collected over the years by Dr. Clifford finally find a permanent home at the Bentley Historical Library.
The records of Delta Sigma Delta provide an interesting view into the organization of a professional fraternity, and into the activities and personalities of those individuals drawn to such a social organization. Because it is such a visual collection, with many photographs, scrapbooks, and artefactual items, the Delta Sigma Delta collection provides a varied source of information about the affairs of a distinguished professional fraternity.
The Delta Sigma Delta collection includes both the records of the fraternity as well as related materials collected over the years by fraternity historian, Dr. Frank O. Clifford, and as such, there is a wide diversity of materials spanning more than a century of activity, 1882 to 1992.
The records of Delta Sigma Delta, at the request of the fraternity, are divided between those records stored archivally and other materials on display in the Delta Sigma Delta Room of the library. This finding aid will describe both sets of records with indications where they might be found.
Subjects:
Delta Sigma Delta.; Dentistry--United States.; Dentists--United States.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Delta Sigma Delta.; Delta Sigma Delta. Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan); Dentistry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Fraternities and sororities.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Slides.
- History/Organizational
  The first series History/Organizational gives some basic historical information about the fraternity, including the 1950 published history of the fraternity and various organizational documents (constitution and bylaws and related materials). Of special note are the history reports submitted to the History Committee of the fraternity from both graduate and undergraduate chapters during the 1950s. These reports include information on membership and chapter activities.
  - History of Delta Sigma Delta Fraternity, 1882-1946 1950
  - Campus Prospectus, 1951 containing history and description of the fraternity's organizational structure (Box 1)
  - Collected correspondence of L.L. Davis and F.O. Clifford relating to the history and establishment of a DSD library/museum and to the fraternity's records 1918-1974 (Box 1)
  - Delta Sigma Delta Library/Museum Planning 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Delta Sigma Delta Symbol History 1882-1937 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions and Bylaws 1882-1922 (Box 1)
  - Fraternity Rituals and Handbooks 1910-1966 (Box 1)
  - History Committee
    - Undergraduate Chapters reports and related 1954-1959, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Graduate Chapters reports and related 1954-1959, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: include diplomas and chapter charters (Box 16)
- Publications
  The Publications series consists of the fraternity's newspaper Desmos, 1894-1975 and 1981-1983 (27 volumes and 2 folders) and a published copy of the fraternity's Alumni Directory.
  - Desmos, 1894-1975, 1981-1983, 2 folders; 27 volumes
  - DSD Alumni Directory
- Organizational Units
  The next series, Organizational Units, includes collected records and memorabilia pertaining to the various organizational divisions within Delta Sigma Delta. Worthy of note is the minute book, 1884-1898, of the Supreme Chapter, as well as scattered minutes of the Council of Graduate Chapters and the Council of Deputies. Within Organizational Units are subseries of materials for the fraternity's graduate, auxiliary, and undergraduate chapters. As might be expected, within this last subseries, the most extensive run of materials relate to the Alpha or Ann Arbor chapter of the fraternity. These also include some of the earliest materials in the collection, dating back to 1885. Included are minutes of meetings and account books.
  - National organization
    - Supreme Chapter: Minutes 1884-1898 and history written by L.L. Davis in 1927 (Box 1)
    - Council of Graduate Chapters Minutes 1951-1963 (Box 1)
    - Supreme Grand Master
      - Papers 1929, 1944 (Box 1)
      - Papers 1930-1931 (Box 1)
        (include speech of L.J. Mitchell, 1931)
    - Supreme Scribe Correspondence 1951-1963 (Box 1)
    - Life Membership Committee 1938 (Box 1)
    - Delta Sigma Delta Educational Foundation (Box 1)
    - Council of Deputies Proceedings 1935-1964 (scattered dates), 23 volumes booklets (Box 1)
    - National Conclave Proceedings and comments re first conclave 1948 (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary Chapters
    - Alabama Auxiliary (Box 2)
    - Boston Auxiliary (Box 2)
    - Chicago Auxiliary, Beta Chapter
      - Minutes 1893-1914, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      - Minutes 1927-1937, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      - Minutes 1937-1942 (Box 2)
        (includes obituaries of members)
      - Proceedings of regular meeting 1912 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Cincinnati Auxiliary Minute book 1916-1929 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Auxiliary Chapter Charter 1895 (Box 16)
    - Detroit Ladies Auxiliary minute book 1949-1963
  - Graduate Chapters
    - Arkansas Graduate Chapter Biographies of members (Box 2)
    - Detroit Graduate Chapter Minutes 1895-1946
    - London Graduate Chapter (Box 2)
    - New Zealand Graduate Chapter (Box 2)
    - Pittsburgh Graduate Chapter (Box 2)
    - Victorian Graduate Chapter, Victoria Australia, History and Biographies (Box 2)
  - Undergraduate Chapters
    - Harvard University, Gamma Chapter. (Box 2)
    - Tufts University, Mu Chapter. (Box 2)
    - University of Detroit, Pi Pi Chapter. (Box 2)
    - University of Illinois, Rho Chapter. (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan (Ann Arbor), Alpha Chapter
      - Constitution and by-laws
      - Record from organization to October 1885
      - Minutes of meetings 1885-1930, 9 volumes
      - Account book 1885-1889
      - Financial Records 1893-1949 (scattered dates), 5 volumes
      - Alpha Chapter Building Association records 1914-1968 (Box 2)
      - Guest Book 1930-1964 (Box 2)
      - "Political Book," 1907 (Box 2)
        (contains agreements between U-M fraternities)
      - 75th Anniversary file 1955-1957 (Box 2)
    - University of Minnesota, Theta Chapter. (Box 2)
- Personal Papers of Members
  Next is a series of Personal Papers of Members, arranged alphabetically. A significant portion of this series is the correspondence of L. L. Furnas, who during 1925-1926 was president of the DSD Council of Deputies.
  - Anderson, W. St. Clair photo album and miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Cleland, William (Box 20)
    (see also album in box 5)
  - Frank O. Clifford (Box 20)
  - Davis, L.L.
    - General. (Box 20)
    - Annual Meeting 1934 (Box 20)
    - Speech 1936 (Box 20)
  - Furnas, L.L. (President, Council of Deputies) correspondence 1925-1926, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Gentilly, James V. (Box 20)
  - Hillenbrand, Harold (Box 20)
  - Knudtzon, Kermit (Box 20)
  - S.G.M. (diary of visit with various chapters 1924) (Box 20)
  - Parr, Leonard A. (Honorary Member) (Box 20)
  - Rogers, Lloyd (Box 20)
  - Weinrich, C.P. (Box 20)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series dates from the 1880s, and includes portraits of many of the fraternity's first members. Photographs can also be located on the wall of the Delta Sigma Delta lounge and in the following series of scrapbooks.
  (see also oversize photos in box 16 and photos on display in DSD Room)
  - Founders 1883 (Box 3)
    (include comments on doctored portrait)
  - Founders 1884 (graduation portraits) (Box 3)
  - Dental school faculty portraits (Box 3)
  - Class of 1886 class portraits (Box 3)
  - Other dental school portraits of graduates 1880s, 1890s (Box 3)
  - U-M campus views 1880s (Box 3)
  - Ward Howlett album circa 1899 (Box 3)
  - Paris Organizing Group 1906 (Box 3)
  - Classes of 1906-1909 at Delta House (Box 3)
    (including exterior view of house at 807 S. State Street)
  - Delta Sigma Delta houses (Box 3)
  - History Committee 1945 (Box 3)
  - Oldsters Reunion 1946 (Box 3)
  - C.P. Weinrich, William Cleland, 68th Organization Day Anniversary March 5, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Banquets and reunions (Box 3)
  - Jackie Jungman Party circa 1934, 2 volumes (in 1 envelope) (Box 3)
  - Album compiled by Dr. Alfred Grob of various Delta functions circa 1960s (Box 3)
  - Photographs originally located in Delta Sigma Delta Room (Box 3)
    (include photos of F.O. Clifford at Bentley Library groundbreaking)
  - Negatives (Box 3)
  - Glass slides of portraits of founders and other early dental school graduates (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Class Photographs, 4 folders (Box 16)
    (includes Alpha Chapter 1885)
  - Photograph: Beta Chapter, Chicago College of Dental Surgery 1915 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous photos (Box 16)
- Scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks includes numbered scrapbooks of fraternity activities compiled by Frank O. Clifford as well as other scrapbooks of early member William Cleland. The scrapbooks are largely visual in content and consist of photographs, programs, and certificates and citations, although there are also a set of volumes containing correspondence of a celebratory or congratulatory tone.
  - Scrapbook A, Alpha Cabinet Card Photos 1882-1897 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook B, Memorabilia, Alpha Chapter 1897-1907 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook C, Banquet and Dance Programs (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook D, General Memorabilia, Banquet and Dance Programs, Supreme, Graduate, and Undergraduate (Box 4)
  - Cleland, William. Album of class portraits 1880s (Box 5)
  - 68th Anniversary of DSD. Scrapbook of cards and letters presented to William Cleland 1951 (Box 5)
  - 72th Anniversary of DSD. Volume of letters presented to William Cleland and C.P. Weinrich 1954 (Box 5)
  - Numbered scrapbook series containing photos, letters, and other memorabilia mainly compiled by Dr. F.O. Clifford
    - Vol. 1. Early documents and photographs
    - Vol. 2. Memorabilia of Alpha Chapter
    - Vol. 3. Memorabilia of Beta Chapter
    - Vol. 4. Various
    - Vol. 5. Past Supreme Grand Masters
    - Vol. 6. Various
    - Vol. 7. Undergraduate chapters (other than Alpha)
    - Vol. 8. Personalities
- Plaques
  - Russell Bunting and F.O. Clifford. (Box 6)
  - Plaques 1954-1975 (Box 7)
  - Plaques 1954-1975 (Box 8)
    (continued)
- Textbooks etc.
  - Textbooks 1854-1887 (Box 9)
  - Textbooks 1890-1904 (Box 10)
  - Dentistry Books 1913-1932 (Box 11)
  - Fraternity Bibles (Box 12)
- Memorabilia
  (also in DSD Room)
  - National Programs 1929-1982 (Box 19)
  - Pins, Ribbons, Michigan Flag. (Box 19)
  - Fraternity pins (Box 19)
  - Dance Cards, 2 envelopes (Box 19)
  - Banquet Programs 1916-1952 (Box 19)
  - Songbooks. (Box 19)
  - Scrolls (Box 19)
  - Ties (Box 19)
- Artifacts
  - Watches, Dental Instruments. (Box 13)
  - Casting Machines, Dental Equipment. (Box 14)
  - Delta Sigma Delta dishes (Box 15)
  - Cleveland Graduate chapter ceremonial cups, 2 cups (Box 17)
  - Sigma chapter mortgage burning glass (Box 17)
  - Spoon set from Australian chapter (Box 17)
  - Memorabilia belonging to Dr. Quentin Ringenberg (Box 18)
  - University of Pennsylvania Dental School class portrait (Item 1)
  - Oil painting of unidentified gentleman (Item 2)